in this video we're going to talk about
non-uniform circular motion
and what is that exactly and how is it
different from uniform circular motion
well let's talk about uniform circle
motion
that kind of motion what we have is an
object
moving
that is a turbo circle but we have an
object moving in the circle
at constant speed
so there's going to be a centripetal
acceleration
so that's uniform
circle of motion
the key word
is constant speed
even though the direction is changing
continuously
now in non-uniform circular motion
the speed is not constant
now the object is still traveling in a
circle
however
it's accelerating it might be
decelerating too
but let's say it's accelerating so it
has not only a centripetal acceleration
but a tangential acceleration
let's say it's moving in this direction
at this point
so that's a non-uniform circular motion
the speed is not constant that's the
difference
so because we have two components
of acceleration the x and y component
there's going to be a resultant
acceleration in that direction at that
point
so the resulting acceleration
is based on
the tangential acceleration
and the centripetal acceleration which
was pointing in the y direction
at this point
and if you need to calculate the
resultant acceleration
is equal to the square root
of the square of the tangential
acceleration
plus the square of
the centripetal acceleration
so that's how you could find it
now what equation can we use to
calculate
the tangential acceleration
is basically the way you would calculate
acceleration in kinematics
is the change in velocity
divided by the change in time
so it's equal to v final
minus v initial
divided by t where t is the time
difference where the speed changes from
its initial value to its final value
so that's how you can calculate the
tangential acceleration
and a centripetal acceleration
you know it's simply v squared divided
by the radius of the circle
so now we have everything we need in
order to calculate everything in this
problem
so let's work on it a 1200 kilogram car
accelerates from rest to a speed of 40
meters per second
in five seconds at a constant rate on a
circular track
of radius 800 meters
what is the tangential acceleration
so let's draw a picture
so let's say this is the car
and it's turning on a track
and the radius of that track
is 800 meters
so we know it's going to have a
centripetal acceleration
that points towards the center and it
has a tangential acceleration
so first we need to calculate the
tangential acceleration
we know the initial speed is zero
because the car accelerates from rest
and it reaches a final speed of 40
meters per second
in the time period of 5 seconds so with
this information we can calculate the
tangential acceleration
it's v final minus v initial divided by
t so it's the change in velocity
40 minus 0 which is 40 divided by the
time so 40 divided by 5
is 8.
so the tangential velocity i mean the
tangential acceleration
is 8 meters per second squared
so that's the answer for part 8.
now let's move on
to part b
what is the centripetal acceleration
now we'll need to choose a speed and
let's say we're looking for the
centripetal acceleration at the final
speed of 40 meters per second
if we choose the initial speed of zero
then there will be no centripetal
acceleration so we're going to go with
the final speed
the centripetal acceleration
is v squared over r
so at a speed of 40
with a radius of 800
it's going to be
40 squared
is 1600 and if we divide that by 800
we're going to get a centripetal
acceleration of 2
meters per second squared
so now with this information we can
calculate the net acceleration
when the speed is 40
because as the speed changes
the centripetal acceleration changes as
well
so when the car accelerates starting
from rest the triple acceleration is
zero
when it reaches the speed of 40 the
centripetal acceleration is now two
and so as it's speeding up the
centripetal acceleration is increasing
as well
now to find the net acceleration we're
going to use this formula it's going to
be the square root of the square of the
tangential acceleration
plus the square of the centripetal
acceleration
so this is going to be eight squared
plus two squared
h squared is sixty-four
two squared is four
sixty-four plus four sixty-eight
so this is the square root of 68
so the net acceleration
that is
the acceleration in that direction
well it's going to be closer to the
tangential acceleration since that is
much larger
than the centripetal acceleration
it's about
8.25
meters per second squared
so now you know how to calculate the net
acceleration
for this type of problem
so now we can move on to part d
so now that we have the net acceleration
of 8.25
what is the net force
acting on the car
well based on newton's second law the
net force
is the product of the mass
times the net acceleration
so in this example
we have a mass of 1200 kilograms
and a net acceleration
of
8.25 meters per second squared
so it's going to be 1200
times 8.25
and so the net force
is approximately thousand nine hundred
newtons
so now you know how to calculate it
now
for the sake of practice go ahead and
calculate the centripetal force
and the tangential force
according to newton's second law
the force and the acceleration factors
are in the same direction
so for an object moving in non-uniform
circular motion if we have a centripetal
acceleration pointed in the y direction
and a tangential
acceleration pointed in the x direction
and let's say this is the net
acceleration
well we're going to have a centripetal
force
in the same direction as a centripetal
acceleration
and we're going to have a tangential
force in this direction
and here's the regular force f
so if you want to calculate the
centripetal force it's simply
the mass times the centripetal
acceleration
so that's going to be
1200 times a centripetal acceleration of
two
so the centripetal force
is 1200 times 2 or
2400 newtons
now to calculate the tangential force
it's going to be mass times the
tangential
acceleration
so that's twelve hundred
times eight
twelve times 8 is 96 so
this is going to be 9 600.
and you can confirm that these answers
do indeed agree with each other
the net force
is going to be the square root
of the square of the tangential force
plus
the square of the centripetal force
so the tangential force that's 9600
and the centripetal force is 2400.
so type that in exactly the way you see
it in your calculator
if you do
you should get
98.95 newtons
which is approximately about nine
thousand nine hundred if you round it
so you can calculate the net force both
ways
you can just do m a or
you can also use this equation if you
want to
it works the same way as the net
acceleration formula
now there's one more thing we need to
talk about
sometimes you need to find the angle
that the acceleration vector makes with
the x-axis
so let's talk about how to find it
so here's the acceleration vector
here is the tangential component and
here's the centripetal component
so let's calculate this angle
so tangent of that angle
is equal to the y component divided by
the x component tangent is opposite
divided by adjacent
so therefore the angle is going to be
the arc tangent
of the centripetal acceleration divided
by the tangential acceleration
so in our example is going to be arc
tangent or inverse tangent the
centripetal acceleration is two
the tangential acceleration is eight
so our tangent of one over four
that's going to give us an angle
of
14.04 degrees
above the positive x-axis
at this position
now keep in mind this angle
might be different based on where you
are in a circle but right now
we're at the bottom of the circle so at
that position it's 14 degrees above
the x-axis
and so that's basically it now you know
how to find everything that you need to
find for problems associated with
non-uniform circular motion so just keep
this in mind in non-uniform circular
motion the object is moving in a circle
and accelerating at the same time
it's not moving at the circle around the
circle with constant speed it's speeding
up as it moves around a circle or it
could be slowing down
so just keep that in mind
anytime there is an acceleration
there is a change in velocity and
velocity is speed with direction
so in uniform circular motion
the speed is constant
but the velocity is changing because the
direction is changing
so in uniform circular motion
all you have is a centripetal
acceleration which is based on the
change in the direction of the object as
it moves around the circle even though
it's moving around the circle of
constant speed
but in non-uniform circular motion
not only do you have a change in
direction but you have a change in speed
the change in direction gives rise to
the centrifugal acceleration
which is always existent for any
circular motion
but the change in speed is as a result
of the tangent acceleration
which is what we have in non-uniform
circular motion in uniform circular
motion we only have a centripetal
acceleration due to the change in
direction but in non-uniform circle
motion
we have the centripetal acceleration as
a result of the change in direction but
we also have a tan general acceleration
as a result in the change in the
magnitude of velocity or the speed
so those are some highlights between the
two and that's it for this video thanks
for watching and have a good day
you